A Guide to the Papers of James Boyd 1938-1941
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of James Boyd 1938-1941
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7684
This collection consists of 37 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Purchase 7684
Biographical/Historical Information
American writer, 1888-1944, known for historical novels, particularly Drums, Bitter Creek, and Roll River.
Scope and Content Information
The collection contains a manuscript of bibliographical notes by Frank Stone on Boyd, correspondence of Stone and Boyd, and photographs of Boyd.
Contents List
- Manuscripts 1938
  - Bibliographical notes by Frank Stone regarding James Boyd's works. ca. 1938, AMs and TMs (carbon) 42 p. (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1938-1939
  - Jacob Blanck to R.R. Bowker Co. to Frank Stone 1938 July 11, TLS 1 p. (Box 1)
    Blanck discusses corrections for Drums, making Blanck's copy correspond with Stone's.
  - Collector's Book Shop to Frank Stone 1938 October 1, TPC (Box 1)
    Collector's Book Shop can offer a first edition of Long Hunt, as new, in dust jacket for $2.50.
  - Frank Stone to Joseph H. Poli of Charles Scribner's 1938 November 9, TL (carbon) 1 p. (Box 1)
    Stone requests correct bibliographical information on specific lines of Drums, Marching On, Long Hunt, and Roll River. He also requests the number of copies in the first edition of each title, and any other data in regards to issues, etc.
  - Joseph Poli to Frank Stone 1938 November 10, ALS 1 p. (Box 1)
    Poli sends the biliographic information Stone requested and notes that Bitter Creek will probably be published in January or February.
  - Frank Stone to James Boyd 1938 November 30, TL (carbon) 1 p. (Box 1)
    Stone is preparing a checklist of first editions of Boyd's books for publication in Publisher's Weekly. He asks Boyd to read the list for errors and would also appreciate knowing of any short pieces that appeared in book form. He notes that there is a demand for first editions and a need for authoritative information on identifying them.
  - James Boyd to Frank Stone 1938 December 15, ALS transcript 1 p. (Box 1)
    No checklist enclosed in letter. Scribner's would know better than he how to identify a first edition.
  - Frank Stone to James Boyd 1938 November 30, TLS and TL(carbon) 1 p. (Box 1)
    Enclosing the checklist. Needs help on Marching On as he has seen copies in three different states. Includes a description of Bitter Creek and asks about the existence of shorter pieces such as short stories, prefaces, etc.
  - James Boyd to Frank Stone 1938 December 28, ALS transcript 1 p. (Box 1)
    Hunting Sketches by Anthony Trollope, Gosden Head, 1928, has an introduction by him. As We Are, a collection of short stories edited by Walter B. Pitkin, contains his Shif'less. Miss [June] Cleveland who has an autographed copy of Marching On is not a friend.
  - Frank Stone to James Boyd 1938 December 30, TL (carbon) 1 p. (Box 1)
    Stone thanks Boyd for information on Hunting Sketches and As We Are. Has written Library of Congress for publication dates as well as information on first issue of Marching On. Would Boyd inscribe his first editions? Mr. Poli has promised him a set of galley proofs, a sought after collector's item.
  - R. E. Roberts, Collector's Book Shop, to Frank Stone 1938 November 30, TLS 1 p. (Box 1)
    The Trollope was published at $10.00 in 1933. Can get a new copy at that price. Three later English editions all have the Boyd introduction. Pitkin, published in 1923, is out of print. Does he wish them to advertise for it?
  - Frank Stone to Valta Parma 1939 January 3., TL (carbon) 1 p. (Box 1)
    Stone writes the Library of Congress Rare Book Curator asking help with the checklist. Needs transcripts of title page and copyright page of Marching On, Hunting Sketches by Anthony Trollope, and As We Are, edited by Walter B. Pitkin.
  - Valta Parma to Frank Stone 1939 January 14, TLS (with enclosed typed memo) 1 p. (Box 1)
    Encloses a memo prepared by an assistant regarding the requested title pages.
  - Frank Stone to Valta Parma 1939 January 17, TL (carbon) 1 p. (Box 1)
    Stone thanks Parma for her letter and memo. Requests transcript of copyright page of Marching On.
  - Frank Stone to Jacob Blanck 1939 February 21, TL (carbon) 1 p. Enclosing TM (carbon( list of Boyd's books (Box 1)
    Encloses Boyd list. Interested to hear what Blanck has learned about Marching On. Stone is also enclosing a list of typographical errors for future use. Has seen copy in wrapper with no mention of publication date as well as the copy inscribed for June Cleveland, a store buyer. Reminds him not to forget the M.F.H. after Boyd's name in Hunting Sketches.
  - Jacob Blanck to Frank Stone 1939 February 24, TLS 1 p. (Box 1)
    List arrived. Asks questions regarding Drums and Marching On. Does Stone want to tackle them?
  - Frank Stone to H.R. Huntting Company 1939 March 16, TL (carbon) 1 p. (Box 1)
    Stone is preparing a checklist of first editions of Boyd's books. Learned from Scribner's that in 1925 Huntting had 250 copies of Drums bound in buckram. Wants to locate and buy one. If that not possible, do they have a copy he could use for comparison purposes? Mentions points he wants to compare in establishing the true first edition.
  - J.A. Bousquet of H.R. Huntting to Frank Stone 1939 March 20, TL (carbon) 1 p. (Box 1)
    Copies of Drums are exhausted and have no records of where copies were sold. Suggests he advertise in Publisher s Weekly.
  - Frank Stone to J. A. Bousquet 1939 March 21, TL (carbon) 1 p. (Box 1)
    Thanks Bousquet for reply. Says his first letter wasn't clear. Does Huntting have a copy of Drums in their library and would they be willing to compare points? A rare book dealer is advertising for a first edition. Scribner's sent them 250 copies of the first edition. Needs to know if they were distributed before the publication date of March 27, 1925.
  - Frank Stone to James Boyd 1939 March 21, TL (carbon) 1 p. (Box 1)
    A question has arisen on Drums. Does he have a copy of the first edition and would he be willing to compare some points which he lists? Mr. Poli of Scribner's has sent copy of the galleys of Bitter Creek and Stone is getting a cop of the first edition. Offers his congratulations on the fine reviews it is receiving. In an ANS note at the bottom of the page Boyd answers Stone's questions from his own copy but does not know if it is a genuine first edition.
  - Frank Stone to Valta Parma 1939 March 21, TL (carbon) 1 p. (Box 1)
    Stone is troubling Parma once more to ask for a transcript of the title page of her copy of Drums.
  - Valta Parma to Frank Stone 1939 March 22, TLS 2 p. (Box 1)
    Two Library of Congress copies of Drums not on shelves. Gives copyright information for third copy. Also includes information for Marching On which is in original binding but greatly worn. Does Stone think it worthy of preservation in the Rare Book Room? Has also found copyright deposit of Long Hunt in original binding. Is that worth transferring?
  - J.A. Bousquet to Frank Stone 1939 March 23, TLS 1 p. (Box 1)
    Scribner's furnished them 250 copies of Drums in 1925 but they kept no sales records. By an understanding with publisher the books were not to be sold before the publication date.
  - Frank Stone to J.A. Bousquet 1939 March 25, TL (carbon) 1 p. (Box 1)
    Stone thanks Bousquet for his assistance.
  - Frank Stone to Valta Parma 1939 March 25, TL (carbon) 1 p. (Box 1)
    Thanks her for her information which corresponds with copies he has seen. Copies are scarce and an advertisement in Publisher's Weekly brought no response. Scribner's published 2500 copies of Drums but because of its popularity the first edition is rare. First printing of Marching On was supposedly 28,000 copies. In addition to 26,000 copies of Long Hunt there was a limited edition of 260 copies published simultaneously.
  - Frank Stone to Jacob Blanck 1939 March 25, TL (carbon) and TMs (carbon) 2 p. (Box 1)
    Stone sends the revised James Boyd checklist. Blanck should feel free to edit his notes under Drums and Marching On. Reminds him to add M.F.H. under Hunting Sketches and requests ten personal copies.
  - Frank Stone to James Boyd 1939 March 25, ALS transcript and TMs 2 p. (Box 1)
    Thanks him for comparing his copy of Drums which he thinks is the second printing and explains why. Encloses copy of the list he mailed to Publisher's Weekly and will send him a published copy.
  - Frank Stone to James Boyd 1939 April 20, ALS transcript 1 p. (Box 1)
    Encloses copy of Publisher's Weekly with the checklist of Boyd first editions. Would Boyd be willing to inscribe Stone's personal copies?
  - James Boyd to Frank Stone 1939 April 23, ALS transcript 1 p. (Box 1)
    Thanks Stone for the list and will be glad to autograph his books.
  - Frank Stone to James Boyd 1939 April 29, ALS transcript 1 p. (Box 1)
    Is sending the books for autographing except for the elusive first edition of Drums. Thanks him for his trouble.
  - Jacob Blanck to Frank Stone 1939 May 10, TLS 1 p. (Box 1)
    Encloses a token of appreciation and esteem though Publisher's Weekly does not pay for checklists. Hopes this will enable him to buy more books and produce more checklists.
  - Frank Stone to James Boyd 1939 May 11, ALS transcript 1 p. (Box 1)
    The box of autogrpahed books arrived. Hopes Boyd will come to New York so he can thank him personally.
  - Secretary of Frank Stone to Jacob Blanck 1939 May 13, TL (carbon) 1 p. (Box 1)
    Wishes to acknowledge Blanck's letter and check in Stone's absence.
- Photographs 1939, 1941, n.d.
  - Photograph 1939., Publicity photograph, 5 x 7 inches. 6 copies.
    Head and shoulders photograph by Pinchot.
  - Photograph 1939 March 12., Newsclipping of photograph, 2 x 3 inches.
    Head and shoulders.
  - Photograph n.d., Group photograph, 8 x 10 inches.
    Group photograph of James Boyd, Stephen Vincent Benét, Marc Connelly and Dorothy Thompson.
  - Photograph 1941 March 18, Photograph of rehearsal of One more free man, 8 x 10 inches.
    Photograph of rehearsal of the radio play includes Margo, Sydney Lumet, Betty Field and Myron McCormick.